<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Krushi Raj Tula - RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[Portfolio of Krushi Raj Tula. A developer, geek, enthusiast, who loves to solve problems and fix things with technology. You can read my writings here.]]></description><link>https://krushiraj.github.io</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2023 07:39:07 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Solving the Wordle Solver]]></title><description><![CDATA[I think there are very less people who are unaware of the popular (at least contemporarily or may be not) game  Wordle . I liked the…]]></description><link>https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/wordle-solver/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/wordle-solver/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I think there are very less people who are unaware of the popular (at least contemporarily or may be not) game &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wordle&quot;&gt;Wordle&lt;/a&gt;. I liked the simplicity and equally challenging pattern of the game. I used to play it to get the final answer right. But eventually the geek in me wanted to write a script that could solve the puzzle without much effort on my brain but a little on my computer’s brain. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find the source code here:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gh-card-wrap&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;github-card&quot; data-user=&quot;krushiraj&quot; data-repo=&quot;quiz-writer-bot&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;loading&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is about the problems that I faced and the decisions I made to get the solver ready for us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Why this?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I found it challenging enough and at the same time the problem statement is very confined so no real intelligence is required. That created the itch in me to solve it just because I know I can do it. So why not give it a try? Also I didn’t want to solve this using the buzzword tech ML, AI etc., not even the deep statistical analysis. Just some overview on data and minimal data analysis and pure algo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Identify the pattern&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are the things that I identified before I started:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem is so finite that there are limited number of 5 letter words in English. Digging into some blogs and source code of the game gives me a definite list of what all those words are. So I know what the possible solutions are, now I have to find a way to point me to the correct one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second thing I found after looking at the list is if we could filter out the words that contain vowels then we will be left with very few guesses to go with&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Repetition of vowels is very less and repetition of any consonant is less and if we found that letter then it is easy to find that word as it narrows down the guess list by a lot&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Choose a starting word that could give a clear estimate on what vowels should be neglected. There is a lot of debate on the choice of first word for the game, but my choice was AUDIO. Because it has 4 out of 5 vowels and it could narrow down a lot of guesses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started on with an array of all 5 words that are gonna show up on Wordle game and I wanted to implement an algo with the observations that I made above. I know can heuristically check each word in the array and conclude the shortlist of guesses. But that was not challenging enough, so I wanted it to be a bit more challenging and optimal. So, I build a Trie, a Trie which can mark the existence of letters and non existence of letters (don’t get confused I check existence and non existence by the search algo I have on that trie).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The solver starts with suggesting AUDIO or any other word (if you want) for the first time and then it runs the search on trie and get backs all the possible results, sorted in the way that has more vowels, less repetitions. Then we can update the game state telling which letter exists in the word, which letter is in correct place and which doesn’t exist in the word&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can have a look at the read me file of the project I mentioned. It will have the visual representation. I’ll attach screenshots here too!
&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/krushiraj/krushiraj.github.io/dev/portfolio/content/writings/wordle-solver/example.png&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So if a letter in 2nd spot is green, I search for all words in trie which should have that particular letter as second letter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a letter in 4th spot is yellow, then there is no point in guessing with the words that have that letter in 4th spot. But also I filter only those words which has that letter in another spot than 4th.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This way we can filter a lot of words and come to a final word which mostly should be the answer in the 3rd or 4th attempt. Some edge cases might lead you to go till 6th chance. There could also be a possibility that we might miss 7-8 words within those 6 chance limit. So, sometimes human intuitiveness works better than algos - this is what I understood after using this script for a day, so I started to print the word that script guesses and then all possible words after that so sometimes we can pick what word to give.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is always fun building such scripts for myself and the learnings that I have with these are immense. See you later, till my next script 😜.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Well Knitted Ecosystem]]></title><description><![CDATA[I’m a big fan of devices and application that are well knitted together on different form factors. I’m one of those nerds who wants to have…]]></description><link>https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/well-knitted-ecosystem/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/well-knitted-ecosystem/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m a big fan of devices and application that are well knitted together on different form factors. I’m one of those nerds who wants to have almost any major form factor device that is available in market. I would love a device if it has better integration and sharing/syncing of data between the other devices that I have. I want my data or apps to be available on almost all the devices I own so I don’t have to feel that I’m missing out on something. So that is the crux on why I love devices which form an ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;My first love for ecosystems&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This started when Microsoft launched the theme for One OS, One Core, One Experience in their software. Windows 8 was their first OS as per my knowledge with this motto. That was indeed my my first love for ecosystem. They had desktop, laptop, phone, phablet, tablet form factors and even a smart watch, which were all supported by this one OS. Eventually Xbox got added. I was literally a fan of that idea and that is when I became the fanboi for MSFT. Except for watch I used all form factors and it was really good to see and that was a great experience, also the syncing of data between all these devices was some kind of magic for me back then. They tried a lot with Windows 10 for this motto and they even added new Mixed Reality devices under the One OS, One Core umbrella. But eventually they couldn’t achieve the final goal what they believed in but that was a great and decent try.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Looking for an alternative ecosystem&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;While MSFT failed to build their own ecosystem, they were quick enough to realise that they need to support the next best option they. That was to create apps and try to build semi-ecosystem with Android devices. They did a decent job in the beginning and that was the only reason I ever switched to Android phone. Discontinuation of Windows Phone was the major reason though. But I didn’t get satisfied with that setup. After a few years I was searching for open-source apps and tried Google ecosystem which was in pre-matured state. I still had the feeling that none of them gave me the experience I wanted. I was a true hater of Apple back then. Because I didn’t feel that they were good enough or they didn’t have a set of features that I wanted. One day I was watching Apple Event where they revealed the upcoming features in their software lineup and all other APIs, SDKs. I must admit that I was pretty impressed. I was equally excited about their universal application just like when I got to know about Universal Windows Platform applications. That is when I felt that this is the new ecosystem that I should try, this is something that MSFT wanted to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Entering the Apple Ecosystem&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not gonna lie, but I was still sceptical about the promises that Apple made about their ecosystem. I was not fortune enough to buy their devices and try everything. My journey started with a MacBook Pro that I got during my intern period. I explored lot of stuff about a lot of things. That is when I decided MBP is definitely a great choice for ambitious developers like me. I was not nerdy enough to go for a Linux one. There is also a reason why I didn’t go that way, because I always wanted something to work “Out of the box”, I don’t want to setup things, they should work with minimal setup. So may that was the reason why I got attracted to Apple.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Finding the perfect Ecosystem&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;After MBP, I used an iPad Pro, which definitely mesmerised me with the continuity features. That is when I made the decision that this ecosystem is what I have been looking for. Then I eventually ended up owning majority of Apple products.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Major use cases&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many people ask me why you’re so mad about the “Ecosystem” thing. Does it really matter? Does it really add value? What do you even do with that? So I explain about what I use it for and they are indirectly the answers for all those questions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Universal apps and syncing data between all devices which is seamless. I can text someone on my watch, phone, tablet and my laptop. Which is a major requirement for me. Also syncing of reminders, notes notifications etc.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Universal Copy, now this feature is available on many platforms but they require setup and which I want to avoid. I want pure seamless integration. I copy on one device and paste on other device, just simple but beautiful.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Handoff and Continuity feature. Let me explain this with a scenario. As part of my job I have to read a lot of documentation and do extensive browsing. Say I opened a bunch of tabs in Safari on my Mac and now I want to take a walk, I just standup and open Safari on my iPhone, voila I have all my tabs from Mac. Not just from Mac but also iPad. So whatever the device is that I’m gonna use for browsing I don’t miss on anything.&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Also if an app is Universal, then I use it on one device and take it other device in the same state with just a single tap.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Setting up devices is so simple that you just tap a button and everything else is taken care of. Though the first device will take some time.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;When you get a new device, you just turn it on while you’re near your other devices, that’s all you should do to integrate and set it up. It just works out of the box with zero or minimal setup.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Seamless switching and connections of Airpods with all other devices&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Using devices in combinations. iPad as external screen for MacBook, Watch to control media and volume, iPhone and iPad as remote for TV, handing off calls from one device to another.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sharing data, passwords, mobile hotspot with other Apple users and devices with just single taps.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Find My to locate all your friends and devices in a single place.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Using Watch to unlock Phone and Mac is the most underrated feature IMO&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not just these but there are many other features as well that keep me in this ecosystem. Though many would argue that X feature you mentioned above in in Y ecosystem. My question to them is does all the features I mentioned above exist in any single ecosystem of devices? That is THE reason for me to finally settle for this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m an Apple fanboi today because the above, if someone else does it better then I’ll be their fanboi. I’m a lover of ecosystem and cross platform and cross device applications. In this digital era all that matters to me is seamless connectivity than some sophisticated features. My respect to all those who build such well knitted and well connected products.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Teachers and Mentors]]></title><description><![CDATA[It's been a long while since I wrote any blog or worked continuously on any side-project. But today I feel like writing this and it was…]]></description><link>https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/teachers-day/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/teachers-day/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a long while since I wrote any blog or worked continuously on any side-project. But today I feel like writing this and it was always on my mind for the last 2 years. So, I thought of writing this as a first step to re-write my daily routine and to check off items in my list that are there from a long time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is &lt;strong&gt;Teacher’s Day&lt;/strong&gt; today and I always wanted to dedicate a writing to all those who directly or indirectly taught me various things in the course of my life. I’m always thankful for what I am today. This particular position that I am in today is somehow due to the impact that various people have had on me. Thanks to all my &lt;strong&gt;teachers/mentors&lt;/strong&gt;. There are a lot of things I learned from various people but there are some striking qualities that I &lt;em&gt;imitated/learned/assimilated&lt;/em&gt; from a few of them. This writing is a special dedication to all of them and I want to list what all I learned from them. I think it would be better if I go in chronological order on how they has an impact on my life and how I changed eventually to become a better person.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Starting with Primary School - I was considered to be a dumb student, at least as per the marks sheet which is the final deciding factor to judge a student in the Indian Education System :P. That is when I gradually ended up talking to my first teacher Mr. &lt;strong&gt;K. Satyanarayana&lt;/strong&gt; who brought a drastic change in me by encouraging and pushing me to study better. If you’re interested in something then the fundamentals of that topic are well known to you and you enjoy exploring it, this is what I believe and he was the one who built the basics strong for my math and a reason for my special interest towards math and problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next is definitely one of the youngest teachers who taught me Mr. &lt;strong&gt;J. B. Ram&lt;/strong&gt;. Probably he is just like an elder brother to me in terms of age but he was the one who pushed me further more. He always said that if you don’t question about something you will never learn about it well and if you think you understood something then you must be in a place to answer anything about it. That was the point where I started to explore things and questioning stuff I don’t know. This quality is much needed for a person who wants to learn things by himself. I should say that he is definitely the first one to indirectly encourage me to go towards self learning which is much required for any person in my opinion. I should definitely share an incident that happened, I remember that one day he was teaching some concepts in Maths and that concept was from the third chapter (assume I don’t exactly remember) and I was trying to solve something that is from fourth chapter by sitting in the last bench. He saw that I was writing something in the notes while he was teaching. He asked the person beside me about what I was doing, just to make sure I’m not doing anything that is not supposed to be done in that class. The fellow beside me had a glance and complained that I was solving problems that are not yet taught (in a tone that I was doing something wrong). Ram sir came to me to have a look at what I was doing and, I was a bit frightened to what he would say. He had look at my notes and said, “Good, that is how a curious student should be. But never do this in class, do it in your free time or you can even come to me so we can do it together”. He also told my fellow mate that there is nothing wrong with what I was doing and his tone of complaint is not necessary. That was the moment I learned that if you are curious enough then there will always be a person who will guide you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By the time I was in High School. I had to move back to my hometown and I was already missing both the previously mentioned teachers. I had a feeling that I would never get someone who would encourage me like that and who would guide me in the way they used to do. I was lucky enough to find Mr. &lt;strong&gt;Satyajeet Rokad&lt;/strong&gt; who definitely was a great guide for me. He was more of an elder friend than a teacher to me. I am very glad that I could finally find someone who can resonate with me and guide me. Until I met him all my education was to gather information and put it out in the examinations to get good rank. But it all changed after I met him. There is a popular quote that says, “Knowing about something is not knowledge, it is just information. Information when understood and interconnected will become knowledge”. He was the one who inculcated that thought in me. Instead of just gathering information he used to insist us to form knowledge base from that. In most of the schools in the area I live they only evaluate and give better graders for your answers to questions in exams if they are almost same to what is available in books. So it all feels like copy writing with a photographic memory. But Stayajeet was the one who used to discourage people who does that, he always use to encourage on answers for questions which are in their own words of their understanding and logically correct no matter the length of the answer. This all led me to become a good self learner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After High School and till graduation I didn’t find a teacher from whom I could learn something that changed my life drastically. Then &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionrnd.com/&quot;&gt;Mission RnD&lt;/a&gt; happened, which I should say has changed my life in many ways. I found great teachers, mentors and  ambitious friends over there. I found &lt;strong&gt;Peri Sir and KC Sir&lt;/strong&gt; there. If I had to write what I learned from each of them and what I learned from all the people from Mission RnD then it would become a mini series of blog posts. In short I would say that I got better at my skills and better at looking at a problem from a different perspective, though it is a math/coding/real life problem. KC always made us think beyond what we could already do. He comes with hard hitting realities that enlighten you. For example you can a couple of views for a problem say, bird’s eye view, straight forward view, blah blah blah but there comes a KC view :D from which you always seems to find the problem very easy and interesting to solve. He reinforces self learning, conceptual learning, and many other important things with his talks. And to talk about Peri Sir, his teachings are always peculiar (so are KC’s) they are fun and always have an inner meaning which is deeper when you listen to the same class again and again, that could be the reason why we and our seniors rush to his classes in the name of assisting him when he is teaching our juniors. There is definitely a lot to learn from him but I always feel like I wish I could attend more of his classes in person. Ethics, Values, Character, Discipline are something that I learned from him (though I’m not completely following discipline now, which I feel bad about). Recently one of my friends, Hari said, “Discipline is something we lack in our day to day life or at least we should have a good discipline in our work life. That is what I learned from Peri sir and Americans during my masters”. I definitely agree with that, we are not completely badly disciplined but we are not at the level of what we wanted to be. I should really work on this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here comes my transition to learning from Mentors after Teachers. One day KC introduced a nerdy guy in our class who was supposed to teach us the basics of React.js. After the class, KC said that the guy’s name is &lt;strong&gt;Aravind Balla&lt;/strong&gt; and he is currently switching to a remote job, also added that he is one of his favorites. That was when I had a hook to that moment and I started learning what a remote job is and who this guy that KC spoke about. I ended up following Aravind on what he did to end up as a good Engineer working for a remote startup. Luckily the fate was so good that I ended up being a colleague to him and a good friend cum mentor. I then came across this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/B3thXqCljSN/&quot;&gt;https://www.instagram.com/p/B3thXqCljSN/&lt;/a&gt; . After which I started looking for people who can indirectly mentor me and then I found &lt;strong&gt;Raghava&lt;/strong&gt; (full name Sai Raghava Acharya indeed an Acharya) who is a friend of Aravind, another mentor that I will never forget. Also, I found mentors in my childhood friends &lt;strong&gt;Sai Peddiwar, Murali etc.,&lt;/strong&gt; I don’t deny the fact that the absence of these people would have affected my life in a very drastic way. I have learned a lot from each of them and I reciprocate them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally the most underrated teacher of my life my mother who is responsible for my self learning behavior which is a quality that I got from here and my father who literally taught me the meaning of famous dialogues ”&lt;a href=&quot;https://translate.google.com/?sl=te&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;text=Viluvale%20Aasthi&amp;amp;op=translate&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;Viluvale Aasthi&lt;/a&gt;” even before that dialogue was out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t mention everyone but the above mentioned are definitely the ones who brought great changes in me to become a better person. On a final note, all I want to say is that there are a lot of people who influenced me who had an impact on me and that is the reason why I am here today and I am glad for that. I want to end this by saying that we can find a lot of people from which you can learn in enormous amounts, you just have to be curious and keen to find them, that’s it.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Building 'Mini-Terminal' for my portfolio]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is an article where I share my experience and the decisions I made while building the  Mini-Terminal . How did it all start? I wanted…]]></description><link>https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/mini-terminal-story/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/mini-terminal-story/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is an article where I share my experience and the decisions I made while building the &lt;a href=&quot;https://krushiraj.github.io/mini-terminal&quot;&gt;Mini-Terminal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h2&gt;How did it all start?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wanted to build a portfolio site for myself, and to differentiate myself from the other popular portfolios found online, I decided to make something which also would showcase my skills in Data Structures, Algorithms and Front-end frameworks. I had some prior experience working with React but none with Vue. So I resolved to work on Vue for this. My goal was to build a webpage whsich would simulate a terminal and file system in a computer. Also, I didn’t want to use any helper libraries or packages to make the terminal. I handled the key press events myself to create an editor. Only elements that were used in creating this webpage were div, span and p.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The UI building blocks&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;First I decided on what components to build. I realised that I should have a container which would handle the key press events. The other components were ReadOnlyText section and EditableText section. In a CLI based terminal you just have text, which is mostly read-only and few parts are editable. This editable text will be converted to ReadOnly once we hit ‘return/enter’ key to execute the commands we give.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The internals that give life to UI&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I implemented a tree with node similar to inode to mock the file-system. I wrote a generic parser and executor components which will parse the text and pass the parsed text as token, which contain some meta data to the executor. The executor will identify the command and execute the function that maps to command. In this way we can have any number of commands and functionalities added with ease in future. Everything was built as generic as possible to extend the capabilities and functionalities with ease. Auto complete suggestions feature was implemented based on the meta data that I had in an object. This is where I have mappings to command names, functions, help text and meta related to arguments and options. This helped me to implement the help command and built a Trie for autocompletion feature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Summing up&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;That was a great experience for me building this because it required me to put in more than one skill to build the entire webpage. My thought to showcase my proficiency in different skills was perfectly potrayed with this webpage because it  required skills like implementation of different and complex data structures, writing algorithms which are efficient and optimal, understanding how Vue components work and communication between the components in the DOM heirarchy, exploring things in JS and CSS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, that’s how the Mini Terminal was built and the story behind it.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[My thoughts on cross-platform/device apps]]></title><description><![CDATA[TLDR; In this article, I will share my thoughts on building modern cross-platform and cross-device applications. What made me to think about…]]></description><link>https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/thoughts-on-x-platform-device-apps/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/thoughts-on-x-platform-device-apps/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;TLDR; In this article, I will share my thoughts on building modern cross-platform and cross-device applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h2&gt;What made me to think about cross-platform and cross-device applications&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent times I had few ideas which would help me make things more simplistic every day. Most of those ideas were cross-platform and cross-device applications. I’ll briefly tell about ideas(if you are interested). Few of my ideas were:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A single application for searching and editing memes. A single repository where you can find meme templates based on search keywords, also smart search based on intents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Universal clipboard(though Apple and Microsoft has it, I wanted it to be true cross-platform). I wanted to build this because I use a lot of devices while working on some projects. I switch between various device types and operating systems while I’m working. I wanted to share the clipboard data from one device to another without being sending it as a message to myself in slack or using a notes app on the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Research and learnings&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I started to think of building applications for these ideas, the first question that hit me was how do I make it pure cross-platform application? I went on in the search of an answer for this, read a lot of blogs, documentations, every possible resource that I could find. I knew about Xamarin, Cordova and few others which are popular for building cross-platform/device applications. After reading lots of articles on the web, I got an answer that is better than any other alternative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My considerations were
Device types: desktops, laptops, tablets, and mobile phones
Operating Systems: Windows, macOS, Linux, Android, iOS&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h2&gt;My decisions from the learning&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;My choice was &lt;code&gt;Electron&lt;/code&gt; for desktop applications and &lt;code&gt;React Native&lt;/code&gt; for mobile applications. You can write beautiful UI for desktop applications using HTML, CSS, and JavaScript, as electron provides the lightweight version of chromium and it renders only that part which used to render web-pages in browser. We can also consume node.js scripts and npm packages to get things done. You can read more about Electron &lt;a href=&quot;https://electronjs.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;here&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. React Native, though it is not as old as other similar libraries but it has something cool which made to stick to this, to know more about it visit this &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.github.io/react-native/&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;link&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The first thing that made me to stick to React Native is you can write most of the UI using a single JavaScript codebase. The second thing is you can consume the native APIs and build JavaScript UI components from native components exposed by each platform. The question for frontend and basic things can be done using the above. You can read more about React Native Bridge over &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.github.io/react-native/docs/0.60/native-modules-setup&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;here&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What if you’re building something that relies on system calls and low-level interactions. In such a case, you might have a question why Node.js based libraries?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, during my investigation, I found that most of the cross-platform applications were written in C++ earlier. And that is the language of choice for most of the developers to have interactions with the system at deeper/lower levels of hierarchy. So, what is the significance, why does C++ even come in the middle of this discussion? The answer is JavaScript might not have the capability to interact with system components, but C++ does have and we can have JavaScript wrappers written for any C++ code that is available and consume it natively in Node.js. This even answers our question to handle the underlying things and processes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;One thing that I want to conclude is that there is no such library to date where you can write once and ship to different platforms and for different device form factors. But, amongst all the choices and gaining popularity for JavaScript and it’s libraries and the community support above decision were made by me.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[React Native Tips Repo]]></title><description><![CDATA[github/krushiraj/react-native-tips This is a repository where I keep on adding new tips and suggestions to work on  React Native . Few of…]]></description><link>https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/react-native-tips/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/react-native-tips/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gh-card-wrap&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;github-card&quot; data-user=&quot;krushiraj&quot; data-repo=&quot;react-native-tips&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;loading&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a repository where I keep on adding new tips and suggestions to work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.github.io/react-native/&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;React Native&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Few of them were taken from several sources on the web when I was surfing to solve few problems I faced. Few are my personal recommendations and suggestions that I felt would be helpful for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you have any suggestions or tips that are not added in the repository yet. Please feel free to raise a PR with all the tips and suggestions from your side. Thank you. 😀&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A bot that saved a lot of time for me.]]></title><description><![CDATA[In 2018, sometime between May and June. I had a remote working internship with  Verzeo Edutech . In the same period, I had to attend the…]]></description><link>https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/quiz-writer-bot-blog/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/quiz-writer-bot-blog/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In 2018, sometime between May and June. I had a remote working internship with &lt;a href=&quot;https://verzeo.in/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Verzeo Edutech&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In the same period, I had to attend the summer course of &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionrnd.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mission RnD&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was able to manage and work on both the things parallelly and everything was fine. But, one day I realized that there were some mandatory quizzes assigned to us and there were only 2 days left before I should finish writing those tests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/lJnAXeJO8tE7E37mxq/giphy.gif&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lazy minds fetch the solutions faster&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started to take the first quiz and felt that almost 80-90% of the questions were of type ‘guess the output for the following code’. So, I immediately called my friend who finished all the quizzes and asked him if my analysis was correct. I immediately got an idea to write a bot to write quizzes on behalf of me. I thought this would work because the passing score is 75% and almost 80-90% questions are ‘guess the output’ types which doesn’t require any human knowledge or interference. I made my mind and started writing a bot for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My choice of language for this bot was python. Because, I’m more confident and elegant at writing code in Python and huge availability of helper libraries are easy to read and write syntax. I chose my language and I have to think of how do I read the questions and mark answers for each of the questions in each test. My answer for this was &lt;a href=&quot;https://selenium-python.readthedocs.io/&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Selenium&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; automated testing framework for python.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, what have I done to make the bot working? It’s just as simple as you can think. You can read about it &lt;a href=&quot;/writings/quiz-writer-bot-project&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;here&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s how I wrote a bot to write tests for myself. Each question had a tricky code and I had to guess the correct output, which would take at least a minute for each question, in the best case. Every test had 20 questions and there were 12 tests lined up for me in the pending tab. So, in the best case, it would be a 4-hour long task. I took around 30 mins to write the code which will do this for me in a few minutes. That’s how I saved my time by spending it wisely by work smart rather than working hard 😜  .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/SLBr5yLzocSYw/giphy.gif&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is how I felt myself when others were writing those tests by spending a lot of time and I wrote a bot that writes those tests for me 😎.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quiz Writer Bot]]></title><description><![CDATA[I have made this project for my personal use and it helped me in a few situations after I wrote this one. You can read about the  background…]]></description><link>https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/quiz-writer-bot-project/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/quiz-writer-bot-project/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I have made this project for my personal use and it helped me in a few situations after I wrote this one. You can read about the &lt;a href=&quot;/writings/quiz-writer-bot-blog/&quot;&gt;background story&lt;/a&gt; about why I built this. You can also find the basic version of the script for the bot at:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gh-card-wrap&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;github-card&quot; data-user=&quot;krushiraj&quot; data-repo=&quot;quiz-writer-bot&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;loading&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this post, I’ll briefly explain how I made this bot and what were the problems that I faced and the decisions I made.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Why this bot&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;First and foremost thing that motivated me to write this bot is that almost 80-90% of questions were based on guess the output types. So, I thought I can write a bot which can directly execute the code that is shown and select the answer based on output. If you want to read in detail about why I built this then read &lt;a href=&quot;/writings/quiz-writer-blog&quot;&gt;Quiz writer bot blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Identify the pattern&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;To the knowledge that I had at the time I wrote this bot, I know that bots are written based on some common patterns for a given task. The common things or patterns that I found in my particular problem were:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;All questions containing code to guess the output were in C (a single language)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Most of the options contained the exact output that we may get when we compile and run the given code. No complicated options that required human intervention to map to an option based on the output.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The DOM pattern was similar to all questions, they don’t have any dynamic class names or ids. So once we have an XPath or a CSS selector to some element it remains the same all the time.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once I had all the information above I tried to fetch the elements by playing for a while in console in developer tools of the browser. With that, I have all the CSS selectors or XPaths ready for grabbing the elements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now I can access the DOM elements that I want but, what about the interactions? How do my bot clicks on correct options and then clicks on the next question, next test, etc.,? To simulate these I chose &lt;a href=&quot;https://selenium-python.readthedocs.io/&quot;&gt;Selenium&lt;/a&gt;, which is used to automate some tests on webpages. My choice of language was python because of 2 reasons, I am very elegant in Python and most of the bots that I heard of is written in Python. So, here is what I did:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Initialize the selenium driver and goto the URL where the online test is hosted. Enter my credentials which are fed to bot through selenium.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Select the appropriate test and click on start test.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Repeat the following steps until there are no questions left else go to step 9.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get the question and find if it contains ‘guess the output’ sub-string.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;If no skip to next question else get the code from &lt;code&gt;pre&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; tag and write it to a file with &lt;code&gt;.c&lt;/code&gt; extension.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Now compile the file and execute it with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/subprocess.html#subprocess.run&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;run&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; method exposed in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.python.org/3.7/library/subprocess.html&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;subprocess&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; module of python and get the output.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Compare the output the options available. Whichever has the exact match select it. If no exact match is found then go for the next closest match. If still nothing matches then go for some random option.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Click on the next question.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Click on the next test if there are any else quit the browser.
I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.python.org/3/library/difflib.html&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;difflib&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for finding the closest matches and &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.python.org/3/library/random.html&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;random&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; module for random choice making.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s how I wrote a bot to write online tests for me in my hectic schedule 😜.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[VCE Results Web-app]]></title><description><![CDATA[In 2018 around mid-June, I was working on Django to explore more about it and trying out some new things and features in Django which I…]]></description><link>https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/vce-results-app/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://krushiraj.github.io/writings/vce-results-app/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In 2018 around mid-June, I was working on Django to explore more about it and trying out some new things and features in Django which I never used till that day. So, I decided to build a couple of web apps to get more familiar with it and to master Python. During this, I build a simple web application where I make some REST calls to an API endpoint which will fetch the news around the world and I processed the data received and displayed it. I wanted to build one more application which would be helpful for people around me. That’s when the idea to build VCE Results was born. Our college results site is the most un-reliable site I’ve ever seen. Soon after they release the results it goes down for no reason(even if the user hits are more or none). So, I decided to build this application so that students can rely on this to check their results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find the repo for this project at&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gh-card-wrap&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;github-card&quot; data-user=&quot;krushiraj&quot; data-repo=&quot;vce-results&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;loading&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The live version of this project is hosted at &lt;a style=&quot;color:indianred&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://vceresults.pythonanywhere.com/&quot;&gt;vceresults.pythonanywhere.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you face any issues in the live version or found any defects please feel free to raise and issue in the GitHub repository’s &lt;a style=&quot;color:skyblue&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/krushiraj/vce-results/issues&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; section. Also, all types of contributions are welcomed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was the time when our results for the end semester would be released in a day or two. So I decided to build it as soon as possible, because I wanted this web app to go live at the same time the results would be declared.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Building blocks&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr/&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Grab Data&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;First thing I had to do was to find a way to fetch the results data from our server. They won’t give me permissions to read the data in the college database from a 3rd party application and they didn’t expose any endpoint to fetch results. So I had to look for other ways, I found scrapping the data from their site is the best possible way that is possible at that time. I wrote a scraper which would grab the HTML code for each of the student’s result page.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Process Data&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now that I have the data in the form of HTML source code. I want it to be in a form which can be easily accessible by the Django backend. To solve this I wrote a data importer script that reads the HTML and parses the data required from me and inserts it into the database.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Giving life to the web app&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final thing is to show the data to the end user of the web app. I think no explanation is needed. Because it’s the most obvious thing and goal of the project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I finished building the application before that night and was waiting for our college to release the results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The release&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr/&gt;&lt;p&gt;As expected the results for that semester were released the next day. I ran the &lt;code&gt;datascrapper&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;dataimporter&lt;/code&gt; scripts to fetch the data and had a copy in my app’s database. It took a few minutes, soon after the process was finished I made the application to go live. I got a great response from the fellow mates, seniors and juniors. While few were appreciating my efforts for doing this, few were busy checking out their results and there were some people(to whom I want to thank) who found few minor bugs in UI and some data inconsistency. They reported the issues which was great feedback for me and that helped me to improve the application.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That was a great experience building this application and making it to go live and iterating over the application features and enhancements from the feedback received.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>